Guide to the New Haven East Association Records
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
New Haven East Association records
1725-1903
GEN MSS 1295
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
5.2
(11 boxes) + 1 art
The collection contains bound volumes of manuscript meeting minutes for the New Haven East Association and the Consociation of the County of New Haven, New Haven East Consociation, Association of the County of New-Haven, and New Haven Union Association of Congregational Ministers. Also present are other records and papers related to the business of the association, its member churches and foreign missions, its mutual improvement societies, and a painted metal box that formerly held the records.
New Haven East Association (Conn.)
Association of the County of New-Haven (Conn.)
Consociation of the County of New-Haven (Conn.)
New Haven East Consociation (Conn.)
New Haven Union Association of Congregational Ministers
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the New Haven East Association, 1887-1903.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Associated Materials
New Haven West Association Records (GEN MSS 1296), Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library.
New Haven East Association
The Association of the County of New-Haven, an organization of Connecticut Congregational ministers, was formed in 1709 following a meeting of twelve ministers and four church laymen called by the colonial legislature. Held in Saybrook, Connecticut, the meeting resulted in the "Saybrook Platform," a new constitution for the Congregational Church in Connecticut, which gave associations the responsibility to examine candidates for the ministry, and to oversee the behavior of the ministers. In 1787 the association was divided to form the New Haven East Association and the New Haven West Association, with the course of the Quinnipiac River as the geographical line. The two organizations were again united by unanimous resolution in 1893 to form the New Haven Union Association of Congregational Ministers in Connecticut. That organization merged with the New Haven Central Association in 1903.
The Consociation of the County of New-Haven, an organization of Congregational churches and pastors also formed in 1709, was devoted to the management of ecclesiastical discipline. That organization, with a membership composed of both church members and pastors, could impose discipline on specific churches and judge disputes that arose. It later evolved into two separate bodies called the New Haven East Consociation (established in 1787) and the Consociation of the Western District of New Haven County (established in 1799).
Scope and Contents
The collection contains bound volumes of manuscript meeting minutes for the New Haven East Association and the Consociation of the County of New Haven, New Haven East Consociation, Association of the County of New-Haven, and New Haven Union Association of Congregational Ministers. Also present are other records and papers related to the business of the association, its member churches and foreign missions, its mutual improvement societies, and a painted metal box that formerly held the records.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: I. Minute Books, 1737-1903. II. Papers of Regional Churches, 1758-1850. III. Other Papers, 1725-1903.
Clergy -- Connecticut; Congregationalism -- Clergy; New Haven County (Conn.) -- Religious life and customs; Boxes (containers) -- United States -- 19th century; Minute books -- Connecticut -- New Haven County -- 18th century; Minute books -- Connecticut -- New Haven County -- 19th century; Minute books -- Connecticut -- New Haven County -- 20th Century; Clergy -- Connecticut -- New Haven County -- 18th century; Clergy -- Connecticut -- New Haven County -- 19th century; Clergy -- Connecticut -- New Haven County -- 20th Century; Association of the County of New-Haven (Conn.); Consociation of the County of New-Haven (Conn.); New Haven East Association (Conn.); New Haven East Consociation (Conn.); New Haven Union Association of Congregational Ministers
- Minute Books, 1737-1903; Series I; 1.04; (3 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Series I is organized into five subseries: Consociation of the County of New Haven, New Haven East Consociation, Association of the County of New-Haven, New Haven East Association, and New Haven Union Association of Congregational Ministers.
  Scope and Contents
  The series contains nine bound volumes of manuscript meeting minutes.
  - Consociation of the County of New Haven
    - Vol. II. Meeting minutes, 1758-1785 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - New Haven East Consociation
    - Meeting minutes, 1803-1823
    - Meeting minutes, 1824-1838
  - Association of the County of New-Haven
    - Meeting minutes (original), 1737-1757 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Meeting minutes, 1737-1757 (manuscript copy made in the nineteenth century), undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Vol. III. Meeting minutes, 1758-1786 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - New Haven East Association
    - Vol. IV. Meeting minutes, 1786-1802 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Vol. V. Meeting minutes, 1803-1823 (Box 2, Folder 6)
      Volume also contains meeting minutes of the New Haven East Consociation (1803-1823)
    - Vol. VI. Meeting minutes, 1823-1838 (Box 2, Folder 7)
      Volume also contains meeting minutes of the New Haven East Consociation (1824-1838)
    - Meeting minutes, 1878-1893 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - New Haven Union Association of Congregational Ministers
    - Meeting minutes, 1893-1903 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Papers of Regional Churches, 1758-1850; Series II; 1.25; (3 boxes)
  Series is arranged in alphabetical order by town.
  Series II contains papers related to churches in towns within the New Haven East Association.
  - Branford, 1795-1850 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Cheshire, 1760-1850 (Box 4, Folder 11-15)
  - Durham, 1794-1850 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - East Haven, 1816-1850 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Fair Haven, 1844-1850 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Guilford and East Guilford, 1841-1850 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Hamden and Mount Carmel, 1762-1771 (Box 4, Folder 20-21)
  - Madison, 1791-1850 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Meriden, 1767-1850 (Box 5, Folder 23-26)
  - Milford, 1780 (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - North Branford, 1809-1836 (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Northbury, 1758-1765 (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Northford, 1788-1850 (Box 5, Folder 30-34)
  - North Guilford
    - Papers, 1760-1850 (Box 6, Folder 35-39)
    - Papers relating to the case of Rev. A. C. Collins, 1789-1793 (Box 6, Folder 40)
  - North Haven, 1762-1785 (Box 6, Folder 41)
  - North Madison, 1785-1837 (Box 6, Folder 42)
  - South Durham, 1847-1850 (Box 6, Folder 43)
  - Wallingford, 1758-1832 (Box 6, Folder 44)
  - Woodbridge, 1765-1850 (Box 6, Folder 45)
- Other Papers, 1725-1903; Series III; 2.79; (6 boxes)
  Series II contains other records and papers related to the business of the association and the consociation, including those regarding foreign missions, cases regarding specific clergy members, and the minutes of meetings. Also present are the minutes of two groups of clergy who met for "mutual improvement" and a painted metal box in which the records were previously stored.
  - Minutes of Council for dismission of Rev. Mr. Gemmill from the North Church in New Haven, 1802 (Box 7, Folder 46)
  - Papers relating to the Convention of Congregational and Presbyterian Ministers, 1766-1772 (Box 7, Folder 47)
  - Minutes of annual meetings of the New Haven East Consociation, 1815-1851 (Box 7, Folder 48-50)
  - Minutes of special meetings of the New Haven East Consociation, 1784-1850 (Box 7, Folder 51-52)
  - Minutes of semi-annual meetings of the New Haven East Association, 1756-1820 (Box 7, Folder 53-56)
  - Minutes of semi-annual meetings of the New Haven East Association, 1821-1850 (Box 8, Folder 57-60)
  - Papers belonging to the Foreign Mission Society of Eastern District of New Haven County, 1812-1821 (Box 8, Folder 61)
  - Papers relating to the General Association of Connecticut, 1762-1800 (Box 8, Folder 62)
  - Dissertations on various topics received before the New Haven East Association, 1725-1850 (Box 8, Folder 63)
  - Miscellaneous papers belonging to the New Haven East Consociation, 1785-1851 (Box 8, Folder 64)
  - Miscellaneous papers belonging to the New Haven East Consociation, 1853-1876 (Box 9, Folder 65-68)
  - Miscellaneous papers belonging to the New Haven East Association, 1780-1848 (Box 10, Folder 69-72)
  - Miscellaneous documents and memorials, 1725-1903 (Box 10, Folder 73-81)
  - Records of the minutes of the meetings....for mutual improvement in the County of New Haven, 1779-1812 (Box 11, Folder 82)
  - Minutes of the circular meeting of the society for mutual improvement, 1828-1865 (Box 11, Folder 83-84)
  - Painted metal box formerly holding records, undated (Box 12 (Art))